A Guide to the Lucian Louis Watt Papers, 1921-1961
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Lucian Louis Watt Papers, 1921-1961
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 12
1.5 linear feet
Lucian Louis Watt
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Department by Mrs. L.L. Watts on October 3 and October 29, 1975, through Dr. Thelma Biddle of the Department of History and Geography (VCU). Additional materials were given in March and April 1977. Newspaper clippings relating to the Virginia Commission for the Blind were merged in August 1980.
Biographical/Historical Information
Lucian Louis Watts (1888-19) was born in Albemarle County, Virginia in November 1888. Son of the Albemarle County Sheriff, he graduated from public high school and attended Fork Union Military Academy for one year. His youth was an active one, and he participated in local sports and served as a deputy sheriff.
Watts was employed at railroad construction work at age eighteen. Within the next three years he became Superintendent of seven miles of railroad construction work. He continued in this profession until a dynamite explosion caused him to lose his sight, May 27, 1913.
Following a recuperation of more than a year, Watts enrolled in the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind in Staunton, October 1914. He graduated from the school in June 1917, and he returned there the following fall to be a supervisor of blind boys. By June 1918, he had became an instructor of industrial work. At the same time he made plans to organize an association for the adult blind. With the help of H. Randolph Latimer of Maryland, and of H.M. McManaway, Superintendent of the Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, Watts organized the Virginia Association of Workers for the Blind, June 9, 1919.
The legislative survey led to the creation of a three-member Commission to study these problems in depth; Watt served as secretary of this temporary commission. The commission was enlarged and made permanent in 1922, and Watt was appointed its Executive Secretary. He was also elected as the first president of the Virginia Association of Workers for the Blind, a position he held continuously throughout his affiliation with the Association.
Watts, through the Association of Workers for the Blind, initiated a financial campaign to establish a workshop for the blind at Charlottesville. Begun in 1925, the Workshop for the Blind was completed by 1930. It was transferred to the Virginia Commission for the Blind in 1936.
Watts served as a member of the Virginia House of Delegates from January 1, 1926 to January 1, 1934. In 1934 he was elected President of the American Association of Workers for the Blind, and after his term ended in 1936 he remained active in the Association, serving on the Board of Directors and as Chairman of the Legislative Committee. He was also a Board member for the National Industries of the Blind. Lucian Watts died....
Scope and Content Information
The Lucian Louis Watts Papers, 1921-1960, comprising ca 300 items, consists primarily of correspondence relating to Watts' work with the blind through the Virginia Association of Workers for the Blind, the Virginia Commission for the Visually Handicapped, and the House of Delegates. The collection also includes speeches and articles by Watts and others relating to loss of vision and education of the visually handicapped.
Arrangement
The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1921-1927 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1928-1932 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1933-1945 (Box 1)
- TMS of Speeches and Articles by Watts 1931-1961 (Box 1)
- Biography of Watts 1925-1953 (Box 1)
- Org. and leg. of Comm. Asso. of Workers of Visually Handicapped 1924-1968 (Box 1)
- TMS of speeches and articles by others 1924-1941 (Box 1)
- Education of the Visually Handicapped 1949-1959 (Box 1)
- Vocational Rehabilitation 1953-1955 (Box 1)
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 1)
- Newsclippings 1939-1949 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous items 1925-1949 (Box 1)
- Printed Documents (Box 2)
- 3 movie films: General Program of the Va. Comm. for the Blind, Pre-School Nursery for Blind Children 1952, The Sight Saving Program in the Pub. Schools of Va. (Box 3)
- Letters of Endorsement 1943-1945 (Box 3)
- Report American Foundation for the Blind and materials regarding rehabilitation and blind workers 1945-1947 (Box 3)
- Articles for Charlottesville Daily Progress regarding Virginia Workshop for the Blind 1946 (Box 3)
- Reports on Virginia Commission for the Blind 1947 (Box 3)
- Notes on special classes for the blind; TMs of Speech Home Teachers; brochure of Virginia Commission for the Visually Handicapped (Box 3)